thing that is it's it's counting down
and it's live. We're live.
>> We're live.
>> Yes.
>> Okay. Bye bye.
>> Hello everyone.
>> Yes. Um All right. It does say we're
live. We have three live. Okay. All
right. We are live. The computer lied to
me. [laughter]
Welcome to Mental Health Monday, guys.
It's It hasn't really been a manic
Monday, but these last few moments have
been kind of manic trying to get live
with you guys, but we are here. Welcome
to Mental Health Monday. Uh good
evening, Dr. White. Good to see you,
Clint. Thank you for being here.
>> You are the first You're the first to
say hello. So, welcome. Please put in
the chat, everyone, uh where you're
viewing from. If you're a first timer to
mental health Monday, we'd like to know
that as well. So, please let us know um
just that you're here and where you are
viewing from. But it's good to see you
guys. I'm excited to uh talk about men's
mental health. We've been having a lot
of lots of fun. People are talking about
it and getting really good advice and
they're appreciating it. and we are I'm
personally enjoying doing it uh because
it's a topic that we don't talk about
enough. It's so very important and we
have to take care of each other but we
definitely need to take care of our men
because um I I think you get looked
over. I think you get looked over.
>> Yeah. I mean it it can be kind of nice.
>> Good. But welcome to u from Buford,
Georgia. Um I don't quite know the name.
I just see the the handle, but welcome.
Good to see you here. Everyone else, let
us know where you're viewing from.
Again, we want to say a special welcome.
Uh, all right. We have a first timer
from North Carolina. Welcome to Mental
Health Monday, Dr. White and we're happy
to We're both happy to see you here.
>> Absolutely.
>> And we are excited to do this men's
mental health talk with all of you. So,
how has your I haven't talked to you for
a week, so how's it been, Dr. white.
>> Uh, I think, you know, I mean, I think
eventful in some ways, uneventful in
other ways, but
>> I'm trying to think my week
>> uh Yeah, my week was kind of probably
pretty much uh the same. Pretty much the
same. Just life is always lifeing. Can't
Can't help that, right? Can't help that.
>> Life is always what? Life is always
what?
>> Life is always lifing.
>> Exactly. Exactly. Exactly.
>> Life is always lifing. meaning it's just
always doing its thing. So life is
always just doing what life does
basically.
>> No, absolutely
>> doing what life does. But um you're
always asking me questions at the
beginning. But before I ask you a
question, I'm going to just invite our
viewing audience to um please think of
questions that you may have and that
you've wanted to ask about men's mental
health. And for women who are here, how
you can help support the men in your
life. Want to say hi to uh brother
Kashif. Welcome. Good to have you here.
Um, looking forward to just doing this
program with all of you and you guys
sharing your questions and Dr. White and
I will do our very best to answer. Okay,
Dr. White, I'm putting you in the hot
seat because you love to do it to me
first, but I'm going to do it to you.
Um, I haven't pre-thought of this
question. So, let's see.
What what do you Okay. What is the
number one thing that you wish
the world and maybe not the world,
women? Because the men in the world
understand, but what do you what do you
what is the number one thing that you
wish women understood the most
about men's mental health?
I wish
they understood
how hard it is to be vulnerable.
>> Good answer.
So, how hard it is for men to be
vulnerable?
if he understood the
>> dynamics of that for you guys,
>> right? It's like it's like you kind of
like society pushes you to be as
invulnerable as possible
>> and the threat is um it's almost like
showing vulnerability is a in the
armor. Like
>> it can be exploited. It can it it's
dangerous. It's dangerous to show any
vulnerability.
And
I think it's one of the first things a
woman will ask, "Hey man, you know, show
me your soft side."
>> Yeah.
>> Um and then
not know
how to handle that sacred trust that,
hey, I just showed you my vulnerability.
Now, in the event that you're super
super angry,
[laughter]
don't exploit that.
>> You know, um I think it can be hard to
then turn around and not use that.
>> Um so, it can be really easy to do when
you're angry. What were you going to
say?
>> Well, no, I was just going to say, I
mean, as a woman, I appreciate you
saying that and sharing that. Um because
I you're right. I think we don't
understand
emotionally how hard that is for for
men. We don't I we don't understand. I
mean,
I would dare to say it's just easier for
us to just be vulnerable or share how
we're really feeling and we don't have
the fear of being misunderstood.
Um
we just let it all out. Um not always in
the right way. many times not in the
right way, but we still let it out. Um,
someone said, um, a gentleman, I think
it's a male, I'm sure, almost, um, I
wish they understood the consequences of
being vulnerable.
>> And what would you say the consequences
are? What is the fear? And would you say
it's fear? It's the fear.
>> The the it's going to come back and bite
you. It's going to come back and bite
you. Like let's say
for example it could be if she gets
angry
>> it could be if the relationship ends and
the person then publicizes you know what
you you need to know this about this
person
>> or you know it's like it just it can
come back to bite you
>> and there's a there's a much more
powerful incentive to just don't be
vulnerable like is this person really
deserving of that,
>> right?
>> I mean, and it's pushed down so far
sometimes you're not even aware of how
to be vulnerable because you're so
accustomed to being defended.
>> So,
so it's a it's a really good question.
It's a it's a really good question.
>> Yeah. Would you say I mean, we're just
going with it. We're just going to keep
going down this road [laughter]
until somebody else answers it. Ask a
question and we keep going with it. So
you think um and men I'm asking Dr.
White but other men in the chat you can
you can uh speak up too in the chat as
well. Um so you think because of the
fear of being vulnerable or not wanting
to deal with the consequences of being
vulnerable they go to another space of
uh defensive to be defensive.
Do you think that's a very sometimes a
number one place to go instead?
>> Well, well, it's like you you might not
have control over it.
>> Um, so you take for example a person who
they're mourning, right? But they have
not allowed themsel to connect with
their emotion,
>> but they've just been stuffing it down
and stuffing it down and stuffing it
down. uh it literally can manifest as
high blood pressure. It literally can
then turn around and manifest as
sometimes a skin disease. Uh and those
are like physical things. Never mind the
aggression that might result. Who here
has not had the bad day
>> and you went home and proverbally
um kicked the cat? Um, so sorry for the,
you know, but like you like who hasn't
like been a little bit more charged in
your response or didn't get the joke or
barked with an int with with an
intensity that really did not warrant
the stimulus, you know,
>> um, because you brought the energy of
that. But
>> if you say you seem upset, oh, I'm not
upset. [laughter]
>> Right.
>> Right. Now, now I'm not going to lie, a
lot of us defend that and prepare for
that, men and women, by requesting a
transitionary period when you get home.
Like,
>> men or women, I think we like that
period of transition. We love that we do
not step off the unit of the hospital,
off the floor of the factory, and step
right into home. That drive home is a
really good thing. It's [laughter] a
good thing
>> because you live in Southern California.
You probably have traffic that you can
[laughter]
>> you you have a nice long drive.
>> Well, [laughter]
I mean like it I'm not going to lie.
It's it's it's but it's moving traffic.
Thank goodness. Like it's moving and so
it's it's moving. Like that's how you
know there's a lot of traffic. We have
different languages for our traffic.
>> Yeah. Um, but it's it's moving traffic,
but it gives you time to decompress.
>> And then when you get home, yet again,
I'll be like, "Don't hit me with
anything new. Just give me one give me
like just 15 minutes to transition."
>> Right.
>> Um.
>> And and and part of that is because I
don't want I don't want you to get the
brunt of the day. I don't want you to
get unfairly treated by something that's
I'm really dealing with and processing,
>> right?
>> Um so, so yeah, the the problem with not
getting in touch with it is sometimes it
erupting when you least want it to.
>> Yeah, great uh answers. Even in in the
chat, you guys are talking about it and
that's very informative um for women.
Very informative.
And Clint has a question. If we break
the cycle of inherited habits and
mannerisms, are our children, boys,
still at risk of those generational
character traits?
>> You want to you want to take a first
down?
>> Um, if we break the cycle of inherited
habits and mannerisms,
okay, are your children, boys still at
risk of those generational character
traits? You know, it it sounds like um
when you're saying inherited habits or
mannerisms, you would have learned that
from your father or your mother or
primary caregiver and you're saying that
those um were negative habits. um if
you've
broken them and your children haven't,
you know, if you've broken them before
you had children and they have they it
wasn't modeled before them, um they're
not going to automatically naturally
have that. So the behavior or the habits
and the mannerisms have to be modeled
before them. So if you're not modeling
it before them, again, they probably
will not have that. But if you have done
that and then in in the middle of that
um had a an experience where your your
behaviors have changed um then of course
they may have picked up on something um
because they saw it. But um it's not
like you cannot work with your boys um
to help them not to go any further with
that behavior. So when we say inherited,
it's it's not really inherited. It's
just inherited by the fact that you saw
it growing up and so you learned the
behavior. So you would have to model it
before your boys.
You have Do you have a take on that, Dr.
White?
>> Well, you said it well and there's
there's not much to add to that. Um,
exactly. I mean, I'm Clint, we are
presuming when you say break the cycle,
it means you're not modeling it. So, I I
would agree with that and I wouldn't add
to what you just said because that was
excellent. Mhm.
>> Um I would I would now further just um
say uh Clint, it it underscores
the profound impact of parenting.
>> Like if you get nothing else from this
like so much so much and tell me is this
the same for you too, sister Tante?
Mhm.
>> So much of the therapeutic interaction
is
tell me about your family, tell me about
what it was like growing up in that
household.
>> Yeah.
>> Like so much stems back to that.
>> So much,
>> you know, so much stems back to that.
And please folk, please
don't like use that don't don't like
sort of like just use that as the excuse
not to grow past it
>> or go beyond it because as a 50-year-old
man I'm sorry I got to start taking some
responsibility now like
>> you know so that that's not what I'm
saying. But what I would really really
encourage is for you parents who still
are like raising children and you are in
a position of influence,
man, take some stock of
how you can impact them meaningfully. Um
because understand that it it is it is a
significant opportunity to influence a
child. Mhm.
>> Um and and I think a lot of times we we
kind of took it for we took it for
granted in some ways. Um I know as a
parent, let me speak for myself, you
know, I look back on opportunities and
I'm like,
>> yeah, I wish I would have spent more
time or I wish I would have
>> um I I wish I would have been more
diligent in
daddy and daughter time like
>> been intentional about let's sit, let's
talk. I wanna I just want to talk to you
just
>> right
>> what what's going on how are you and
scheduled it almost almost as rigidly as
we do therapy like not to do therapy but
>> but to be that intentional about right
>> we need to meet and talk regularly
>> I I wish I would have been more diligent
about that [cough]
>> yes we all have things that we can go
back and say we wish as parents that we
wish we would have done done better
there's know um well the Bible we have
the Bible [laughter] that can help but
we don't have um we don't have a manual
for people say you know you don't have a
manual for each child because each child
needs a little different manual you know
it's like this is how you put this child
together and we had four so it's like
okay I needed four different manuals
[laughter]
could have the general principles that
are all the same but then the detail for
every child was going to be just a
little bit different, but please put
your uh questions uh in the chat. We'd
love to answer your questions about
men's uh mental health. But we have one
here, Dr. White. Impact of social
isolation. Men are often socialized to
be self uh I'm sorry, leading I'm sorry,
to be selfre reliant leading to
isolation. Self-connections and
friendships are vital for mental
well-being and can combat feelings of
loneliness.
So, let me think about that statement
for men. They're they're trained to be
uh self-reliant to just rely on
themselves, not to rely on other people,
which causes them to selfisolate a lot
of times. What do you think about that?
Well, [cough]
it's it was funny because we woke up the
other night and like the power was off,
>> right?
>> And it was it was so like catastrophic.
So, sort of like, you know, it's
terrifying. And you look out in the
neighborhood and the whole neighborhood
is dark and what it really does it it
obliterates this this falsehood of like
self-reliance.
>> You're not re you are relying on. so
many things especially if you're living
in a city for example you're relying on
so many people so many contributions
like what really can you do
independently
>> um I'm not it's not like I'm aloof to
the idea of self-reliance but so
let's just get that out there that it's
this myth that okay I can be
self-reliant if you plan on doing
anything at any level of meaningful
significance, you've got to work with a
team. You've got to work with a team.
There's no question.
>> There's no question. And if you're the
lead, then you're kind of more visionary
and you have to get really good at
finding people to execute. Yet again,
you have to rely on people. So this
notion that you can in some way get
through life and not in a healthy way
depend on others is ludicrous. And God
designed us for relationship. I mean you
see it plainly in Genesis.
>> It is not good for the man to be alone.
It's like we we're we were designed for
community
>> connection. We were designed for
connection. Yeah, we're designed for
connection and and and collaboration.
You get this person here who all they
care about is baking bread. You get this
other person over here, they're super
passionate about painting. You get this
other person who sings
>> like and and and that kaleidoscope when
we come together, the experience is so
enriched.
>> It there's just this automatic
interdependence. So
>> the the goal and I think that's what it
comes down to. the the goal shouldn't
necessarily be self-reliance. The goal
should be what do you want to achieve
and what can you achieve meaningfully
>> just relying on yourself.
>> Um I'm sorry not very not very much.
>> Right. Right. And and I want to say
before we go to this question, this next
question is really good as well, but I
just wanted to follow up on that what
you were saying like I mean um because
men are trained to just depend upon um
theirelves. I mean it's like they don't
even think to so they don't even think
to reach out and the closest person
maybe to them is like even to ask to
just even their um their wife or their
partner um in the marriage like they
don't even think like let me lean upon
you a little bit more and I don't mean
like lean upon like
just emotionally just talk things out.
So, even though you're stressed and
you're worried, you could still have um
you know, you could say, "Hey babe, like
you know, I'm you know, if you're a
Christian, you could say, "Hey, pray for
me because I'm, you know, feel like I'm
taking everything on and I'm I'm feeling
overwhelmed or whatever." Like men don't
even want to say that. Does that Does
that make sense? like to make um just to
depend on and when I say depend I just
mean like to reach out and to connect
with their significant other um and just
let them know that they are maybe even
afraid or scared like men don't even
want to say that because it doesn't seem
manly but you don't always have to have
it all together. Um, you know, you can
say like, "I'm I'm going to do this. I
want to do this, but I'm afraid. I do
have some fear." Like, admit to that and
just feel like at least that's off their
shoulders that um thinking like their
family is looking at them like I have to
be uh the strong warrior all the time,
like to be vulnerable.
>> Well, you know, it's it's funny because
it it all starts with acknowledgement.
It all starts there. It it it it start
like the the door opens. The journey
begins with if if you in a meaningful
way
can grab your man's attention
>> and communicate in the language that's
meaningful to them. Man, I see you
>> right
>> and I appreciate what you do. I app I
appreciate that you fight so
aggressively for our family.
>> Like I'll tell you there's some core
things every man is looking for. Number
one, um a a man is looking for his
father to say, "Congratulations.
>> Yeah,
>> you you did it.
>> You you've exceeded me."
Like that is a sentence that so many men
have not gotten
>> and will not.
>> You just you you you just said
something. We need to do a whole episode
on
um just men that have grown up in homes
of without a father because I think that
is I mean it affects women of course but
just we're since we're talking about men
in this series I think we should talk
about that because that's huge.
That's huge.
>> It's this invisible competition like
every man, you are trying to outdo your
father, not in a bad way, in a great
way.
>> I'm going to take everything that you've
given me and I'm going to take us to the
next level.
>> Yeah.
>> And when a father takes the time to
communicate to that, son, you did it.
Congratulations. I respect your manhood.
That's huge.
>> That is the next one. The next one
though is the woman that he's chosen. If
she turns around and she's like and
she's like, "I see you. I thank you. I
appreciate you." First of all, guy's
like, "Who you talking to? You talking
to me?"
>> Yeah.
>> And she seriously is able to be like,
"No, I value what you're doing for us.
>> I see you. I, you know, and I want to
mirror it. I want to partner with you in
that.
>> Um,
it's it's mind-blowing.
>> Yes.
>> It's it's mindblowing. It's like the guy
like, and again, it's not just like you
sound therapeutic or you sound clinical.
No, I mean like how you guys get down in
your language, in what you know is
meaningful to your spouse.
>> Um, and then imagine behavior that's
actually congruent with that
acknowledgement where you're like, "No,
I really value you. I'm not just viewing
you the way society is pushing me to
view you. Like
>> society like pushes that the view of men
is he's just some numb skull. He's got
no real feelings. Um he's just there to
provide, you know,
>> and we we get and we get the message,
>> right?
>> We get the message. And when you when
you turn that on its head and you do see
that person, that can often be the
beginning of a person saying, "Oh my
goodness, I can trust this person. If if
I can't trust you to see me, what should
I trust you with?
>> I I can't even trust you to see my
efforts."
>> Right. Right. Yes, we need to. Yeah,
that was that's perfect. That was good
answer. Um All right. So, we have
another question. And how do we help as
a mother our older sons in their early
20s who are struggling mentally,
especially the 21-year-old with
relationships? I see a lot of his anger.
I feel a lot I feel a lot of guilt from
from a toxic marriage.
>> That was
>> Yes. Um well,
okay. while you're processing it, uh,
too. I'm still kind of processing it as
well, but um,
you know, as a as a mother and you're
seeing these things in your in your son,
you said you see anger, um, and the
21-year-old and you know where that um,
you you you know where that's coming
from um, because they saw a lot of
things go on um, in the marriage that
um, like you said was toxic and wasn't
healthy uh, for them to see. And so, you
know, the answer is really going to
sound um simplistic, but encourage them,
love them, of course, um
and encourage them to um seek therapy um
because
they need to deal with what happened in
the in the marriage between their
parents um because it was definitely
traumatic for them. Um, and I don't know
the underlying issues of why they're
angry, but it was it was toxic. So
there's, you know, they're angry for uh
the things that they saw uh and
experienced. And so, um, therapy is
definitely going to be can be very
extremely beneficial and just to have a
space where they can say how they're
feeling because they probably felt like
they never could say how they were truly
feeling or if they wanted to say it,
they weren't saying it um in the right
in the right way. They were saying it
with a lot of anger. So, it wasn't being
taken um in the right manner and there
wasn't um healthy resolutions that could
be dealt with whatever they were going
through. So, um, because you're saying
you see it in their relationships, I
guess the romantic relationships they're
starting to enter into, you def
definitely want to encourage them
because it can very much so become a
cycle of what they saw. They can take
that into their relationships. Dr.
White, do you have any thing you would
like to add to that?
>> Well, I'm I'm glad you mentioned the
therapy part because that that's super
important. Um, you know, just in a word,
anger.
Anger is anger is so dangerous.
Like anger is so dangerous. Talk about
we could do we could do something just
on anger. Um, for for my patients, I'll
often kind of draw a balloon
and, you know, basically show them that
life has a life is really good at kind
of filling that balloon up with anger,
>> you know,
>> and unfortunately
the the the world that we have today,
it's not just clear space for that
balloon to just float around unbothered.
There are a lot of pin pricks all
around. You know, there's the pin prick
of dealing with traffic.
>> Um but but there's often pin pricks in
relationships.
>> And if you're not with a person who's
emotionally like intelligent, sometimes
they will actually
be sources of, you know, pin prick for
the anger. Like people will know that
this is a way to push your button and
they'll push that button.
>> And when a balloon encounters a pin,
it's at risk of exploding.
>> And when it explodes, obviously it's not
just the thing, you know, it's not just
a pin that's going to get blown away.
The balloon itself gets destroyed. And
what I'm saying is when we erupt in our
anger, there's a piece of ourselves
we're destroying in addition to the
things around us. So anger is very
dangerous. But here's something that I
don't think people are aware of as well.
>> Anger and the explosion is also
addictive.
>> It's also addictive. Now, why would you
say it's addictive? Because it can kind
of feel good for about three seconds. It
can feel really good to erupt.
>> It was there and you just let it out and
you're feeling this false power and
you're seeing people cower and tower to
you because you erupted
>> and one can start to get addicted to
that experience and not even be aware of
it. By the way,
>> um I got an anger issue.
Um,
all of this is dangerous because
>> people who can't control their anger
are at risk of getting placed with other
people who can't control their anger.
It's called jail and prisons
>> and it's not a pretty situation.
So, so not only do you end up destroying
your life, destroying yourself, hurting
the people that you love, and I'm sorry,
sorry doesn't always fix it. So, this is
why I'm I'm really shining a spotlight
on the problem with anger and as best as
possible, not making it a badge of honor
to say, "I have a bad temper." Okay,
that's not a No, it's it's something
that should be addressed.
>> You want to understand what's the source
of the anger. You want to understand
what your triggers are and you want to
identify the behaviors
for how to strategically and effectively
deal with being triggered. You want to
neutral. You want to
>> you want to get the air out of the
balloon therapeutically, not not the
explosion. You want the air to come out
because you figured out how to untie it.
And that's what happens in a therapeutic
setting. We figure out why you're angry.
What are the things that trigger you and
what are more adaptive? What are more
productive? What are more truly powerful
ways
>> of responding to being triggered? So,
how do we as a mother um deal with the
sons? Well, um, one of the things I
think every mother should, you know,
have this conversation with your son and
for those where a father is present,
um, it's making it clear, son, at no
point should I ever, ever
be in fear of my safety as it relates to
you.
>> Like, never,
>> never. I don't care how upset you get. I
don't care how triggered you might be. I
am one person who should never be tense
because you're angry and in your
presence. In fact, my anxiety should go
down in your presence.
>> And yeah,
if you got to start at 21, you got to
start at 21. But this is a training and
a culture that should be built from the
womb.
>> I'll see like mothers playing and their
kids are like slapping them in the face
and it's like you're like that's not
funny,
>> right? That's I don't care that they're
a toddler
>> like from they should be they should
they should be
uh grown in the tradition a young man
protects his mother
>> and when he's disciplined in that it'll
be easy for him to extend that to his
sister and to his aunts to his wife and
then to his co-workers eventually. that
you understand that no, this is no that
that's that's that's just the culture of
who I am.
>> Um I don't I'm responsible for my anger
and I'm not supposed to let my anger
cause intimidation especially in
females,
>> right? No. Um I also want to um add on
>> backed up by their father. their father
so you can understand how powerful is
the father or the grandfather or the
other men in the family. You should
reinforce that culture, right? Over to
you, sis. Over to you.
>> Right. No, I was gonna say because um um
she also posted, "I feel a lot of guilt
from toxic from a toxic marriage." And
then I think she put in the chat as well
um that her and her her mom the his the
son's grandmother also encouraged him to
get into therapy, but they have not been
successful with that. So, I was just
going to say also because you're asking
like what else you could do and this is
huge. Um because really it has to be he
has to he's 21 years old. He's going to
have to be an adult and eventually say,
you know what, I do want I do need to to
talk to somebody. I do want to get help.
You're right. You can't force them. But
the thing you can do is um you can lead
by example. I don't know if um if you've
been in therapy, it was a toxic
marriage. You know, even you know, I'm
sure um there could be need for therapy
there just for you to to deal with
things. And maybe you've already done
that and that's great if you have
already done that. Um but another thing
that you can do um as a parent is we all
make mistakes. We all because the the
sons seeing a toxic marriage. I mean I
know you didn't enter in the enter the
marriage to for them for the marriage to
go that way but that is what happened
and so when things um happen um as
parents it means so much to children
even they know they're not expecting
perfection from their parents and when
we do make a mistake or things are going
wrong in the home and we actually go
back and say you know what son daughter
I apolog apologize for my part of
whatever you know the situation was and
just that it's huge because that can
soften your son's heart enough where
he's like okay mom is is you know
apologizing for the some of the things I
went through um because the marriage
went south um and again that could
soften his heart to be like you know
what I I I do want to get help or he may
be open to listening to what you are
suggesting to him. But
um it has to be like you said it has to
be his own decision. You can't make him
but apologizing to our children where
it's needed or where we can honestly say
you know what hey I could have done this
better. It goes so far um with our
children. I know I've had to apologize
uh for things. We have four adult
children. You know, I've had to
apologize for things and when I do
apologize, they're, you know, it's
always like, "Oh, mommy, it's okay. You
know, nobody's perfect, whatever." And I
really needed to apologize, but they get
almost so emotional that I'm kind of in
that seat, in that space, but um it it
just it does do something to their heart
and to their mind. And it it it allows
them to see that see their parent being
humble and um and God can do the rest in
their heart. I've seen that.
>> Well, I do think it's it's powerful.
It's being vulnerable. I think it's
incredibly powerful. Now, Toka, so
uh Sister Tante mentioned the therapy
part. Um and it's critical and I'm I'm
emphasizing the conversation part. Um,
and what I'm talking about is once a
child hits 18, they are rapidly moving
into the zone where an ongoing
relationship is now a choice.
I and I and I hope you get that an
ongoing relationship with our adult
kids, it's a choice on both ends. And
many parents have had to crash into the
reality where kids are like, I'm not
going to associate with you anymore. I
have the power not to and I'm not going
to. And so I think we're aware of that.
But the flip is true as well. And this
is where what I'm saying is a woman does
have the power to say, look, one of the
prerequisites for me being in the
presence of a man is I need to feel
safe.
I shouldn't have to tell you that, but
that's true for you, too. I should not
feel unsafe as a woman in your presence.
Number one. But number two, um even as
it extends to me, but the women in
whether it's your romantic partners, you
they should feel safe
>> always
>> and and that should alert the person,
man, if I'm struggling with that. It's
non-negotiable. I got to work on that.
>> I got to work on that. And so sometimes
there's the heat of the moment and that
might not be the time to talk about it
obviously, but then when things calm
down,
>> what was happening you I really felt
like you I feel unsafe right now. Like
what what's really going on?
>> Um and do you do you realize how you're
coming across
>> and do you care? Do you care? Um well
hopefully obviously the person does
hopefully but at the same time yes you
then do have to ask yourself the
question okay well what limits do I need
to set because once our kids are adults
now it's a choice now I'm choosing to
award you with my presence if I will and
I'm being graphic um just to really
stress the point obviously we all want
to nurture wonderful relationships with
our kids but I'm saying Don't embrace
toxicity in order to do that. Set the
limits because it will help them in the
long run
>> and the issue of anger is a dangerous
one.
>> I want to say this uh to Cara followed
up and said um that she thinks they as a
family they really need uh family
therapy and yes that would be great. She
said even um her ex-husband, the father,
I mean, if he's mature enough and
willing to do that, family therapy would
be amazing uh for your situation. But we
have another question. Um how can I as a
father bring control back into the home?
Especially my 17year-old son. He's doing
all the wrong things. Has a lot going on
with school, church, friends, especially
a girlfriend. What can I do? Wow. That's
a lot.
>> That's a lot.
>> Profound question. Well,
>> it is. We probably need a little bit
more.
I mean, you're saying he's doing all the
wrong things. A lot going on in school,
church, friends, girlfriend. I mean,
that's that's a lot. I don't I probably
need a little bit I would need a little
bit more context, I think. Like a little
bit. But go ahead, Dr. White.
>> Well, it would it it would it starts
with get a clear picture of what control
means. like get a get a get a clear
picture of you know what if if I was all
powerful
what would control look like if I was
all powerful and there's a and I could
video camera um if I could video record
the control what would I see what would
it look like
>> and then you take that to prayer then
you take that to prayer okay Lord this
this is what I'm wanting
>> and we are far away from that right now
>> um and you you start that conversation
from a spiritual standpoint.
Um, and then you can start taking a look
at, okay, well, what's going to be the
therapeutic intervention? What might be
the coaching intervention? And what
might be the conversations that are
available to me? Uh, parents, I want to
remind you that you're providing these
kids a commodity.
Free room,
free board. Many of us are committed to
them financially, you know, more than
willing and willing to provide whatever
financial resources I can to help you
self-actualize. And the only payment I'm
requiring is
>> you do good in this world. That's the
only payment.
>> That's a pretty good deal.
>> That's a pretty good deal,
>> right? And so
yes, you you do have some leveraging
points, but yeah, I I think there is a
conversation to be had in terms of hey,
what are the boundaries I want to set?
But it does start with get the vision of
what control would look like,
>> right?
>> Definitely involve God in the
conversation and then start teasing out
what's the role for therapy, what's the
role for boundary setting, what are the
non-negotiables.
>> What are the non-negotiables? like you
know in in in in in our home safety is a
nonnegotiable that's not up for
discussion. Um we all need to be fa uh
feel safe. Okay.
>> Right.
>> Yeah. Thank you.
Yeah. Go ahead.
>> Oh yes. I'm sorry. But he's giving us a
little bit more context. He's saying
late nights on his phone
vaping being disobedient and dishonest
uh with us.
Okay. So, yeah, I think what you what
you what Dr. White already listed out uh
can cover those things. Um,
you know, yeah, you just have to put
boundaries. I mean, he's 17 years old,
late nights on his phone. Uh,
the vaping is is very serious. Not just
ma because of his health. I mean, vaping
is so um
so unhealthy for us physically. Um I
even dare say I will say even more so
than marijuana. Marijuana is not good
for our health, but vaping is is pure
chemicals going right into the lungs.
And so these young people are getting
very addicted. So, you know, setting
boundaries um
for, you know, for your son. Why is he
um why is he vaping? And um
again I think I mean I want to you know
therapy I mean again it sounds so
simplistic but there's so many things
that these young people are going
through and that is being modeled before
them um into why they are you know I've
talked to young people who are addicted
to vaping and you know they they think
it helps them with their anxiety. They
think it helps them with their anxiety.
I mean it's like a false um from what
I'm understanding. Maybe Dr. White can
give more to that to the chemical uh
>> oh if you if I mean it's just so
interesting because what'll happen for
example is let's use marijuana. So
>> uh so people will say marijuana relaxes
me. Right.
>> Right.
And what's what's interesting about that
is even if it does you know provide some
relaxation
in its absence guess what happens
the anxiety worsens.
>> Mhm.
>> So you you see the loop. It's very
simple what I just said like so when the
when the person smokes maybe it maybe it
maybe it reduced their anxiety because
some people get paranoid actually
>> right? But let's say it did relax them.
What'll what the what'll happen
eventually is in the absence of the
drug, they'll have more anxiety.
>> Mhm.
>> So it it it's a feedback loop where it's
like, okay, well now to feel calm
>> rather than using the tools using tools
to calm myself down.
>> Now I I the people become more dependent
on the marijuana. So, for example, and I
mean, and it's, you know, kind of
similar with cigarettes in that you just
that becomes your coping skill to calm
down.
>> Um, rather than you using the powerful
mind, the powerful mind you have,
>> um, and the numerous behaviors you might
engage in that would naturally reduce
your anxiety.
>> Um, so,
>> uh, so yeah. So there are some really
powerful and interesting dynamics that
occur in a home. There are things to be
leveraged. Um, and there's a way to
facilitate the discussion. And so it's
but it's nuanced. And that's why you
want
>> a professional that's hyperfocused on
your family dynamics to then give you
the counsel on how to leverage the
dynamics. um when it's time to speak,
when it's not time to speak, what might
be the issue that you want to start with
as opposed to starting with the wrong
thing, what's negotiable, what's a
non-negotiable. These are some of the
customized and nuanced, you know,
questions that need to be answered in
your situation. Um
well, there's a there's a person in the
chat to whom I have to give some
deference uh because I sleep with her.
[laughter]
>> So,
Well, let me see. Um, and that's none
other than nurse nurse Florence. Okay,
so let's go to your question. Nurse
Florence says, "How do we contend with
these issues while trying?" So, I I'll
the I'll read that the text is you said
your contribution before that and you
said, "When men are not vulnerable, even
the most basic things about their
feelings can be misunderstood." That's
actually a really powerful statement
because when we're not, and this happens
when we're not talking, have you ever
gotten into a fight? You don't have to
say yes. Right. But have you ever gotten
into a fight and like you were not
talking?
>> I Let me confess. Right. Right.
>> All right. Okay. Let me confess.
>> I'll confess, too.
>> And so we weren't talking. Right. And
then because we weren't talking, we
completely misunderstood something.
[laughter]
>> Yes. you know, you completely
misunderstood it and it's like, "No, no,
that's not what I was saying." Oh. Oh,
okay. And it's like, and then you start
talking again and you can actually clear
the air. And yeah, so I agree with nurse
Florence that like when when we are not
taking the time to understand their
vulnerability, a lot of things can be
misunderstood. So, for example, with me
not communicating my vulnerability, a
lot of times it was it was interpreted
as anger, you know,
>> right?
>> As opposed to, oh, no, actually, he's
just really hurt, [laughter] you know?
>> I was just going to say that anger comes
out, but it's really you're hurt.
>> Yeah. And
men don't well I said women do but men
have a difficult time expressing the
hurt part and they and they just it
comes off as anger
>> like when can you imagine
>> fear they don't know how to translate
fear either it comes off as anger
>> can can you imagine a man saying I am
afraid
>> can you imagine a man actually like
saying
>> we should be able to imagine it it would
be a healthy thing but society has made
it has just poured it into the minds of
men that it's not healthy, that it's not
manly.
>> Think how many times
>> I'm afraid.
>> You've seen your man explode, but think
how many times has they just said, "I
feel deep shame right now.
>> I I'm really ashamed right now."
>> Um that that's language you don't hear
and so things can easily be
misinterpreted. And so nurse said, for
example, rather than a man saying to
something you said or did hurt his
feelings, he may be disconnected or
aggressive. Exactly. Sometimes you just
disconnect when your feelings get hurt
and this will create a new set of
interpersonal issues. Completely agree
because and again as a person who's like
I'm responsible for my feelings and I'm
like I don't want to erupt right now so
what I'd rather do is just be quiet,
>> you know? And so of course the tension
is palpable.
>> Um and you're coping, you're trying to
deal with this.
>> Um but of course it can set off
misunderstandings. So, nurse for then
said, "So, how do you contend with these
issues while trying to be emotionally
safe yet connected in relationships?"
Well, what I would say, Nurse Florence,
who is now Dr. Florence, by the way,
shout out to Dr. Florence.
>> Um,
in like relationships have es and flows.
They go up and down.
>> And so, sometimes
>> that you said that. I said that the
exact same thing today. I said, "A
relationship is like going up high
mountains and then you go on this
straight long road and then you're going
to hit another mountain. It's going to
be really high and that that's just the
relationship." Anyway, I said that exact
same thing.
>> And that's just the way it goes, right?
Well, what I'm But but it's sometimes
when it's on the low parts, when there's
not emotional charge, those are
sometimes some good moments to decode
and understand and connect. You know,
sometimes it's the pillow talk where now
we're not trying to fight with one
another. We're just trying to understand
one another and we're just trying to
decode.
>> So sometimes those down moments, those
easy moments can be a great time to say,
you know, to to ask those questions. Um
when you feel ashamed,
>> how do you tend to behave?
>> And what are the things that make you
feel ashamed? Um, what are the things
that like we talked about it last week,
what are the things that make it easier
to talk to me and what are the things
that make it hard to talk to me?
>> Uh,
like I do a communication workshop where
uh, one of the things we talk about is
listening to a person's heart and and I
and I and I've heard you mention that
like
>> Yeah.
>> but like
>> put your ear to their heart.
>> That's powerful. But it's great visual
though. It's a great visual like
>> and and what you would do is you would
stop being hung up on the words that
might be inaccurate or might even be a
little charged
>> and you would you would actually zero in
on what are they trying to say?
>> What are they trying to say? Let me like
really kind of listen to your heart. Um,
so I I think uh nurse
>> I think nurse
>> doctor
>> I think Dr. Florence um
it's it's communicating especially when
moments are easy
>> to understand your codes so that in the
heat of the moment you can interpret it
more accurately.
>> Yes, absolutely.
>> What are your thoughts sister Tante?
Well, I was just going to say I like to
share u when we're talking about, you
know, couples that with couples is that,
you know, you're on I love using sports
analogies because I love sports, but
[laughter]
I like to, you know, share with them
that you're you're on the same team. And
so, learning how to support your
husband, your teammate, so that he can
be um the emotionally best version of
himself. So yes, asking those questions
like what do you need from me? How can I
help you to feel more secure, more to
feel more safe that you will just open
up or just you know just feel more
comfortable sharing things that you're
needing so I can because we're on the
same team and we're teammates and we
want to win together like you know Steph
Curry is my favorite, right? So Steph
can't win by himself. He needs like
everybody else's help on the team.
teammates have to help each other out.
And so women, as you're here listening
about men's mental health, you're
wanting to learn and even if you're not
in a marriage relationship, let's just
say it is uh a brother, sister, like you
love each other, you're on the same
team, figure out how you can support the
man in your life,
>> sister Tante, I was thinking about you
about maybe a week or two back and your
love for Steph Curry, right?
>> Okay.
You're making it pretty dramatic. I
don't know if it's going to say the
love. I don't know if you I have the
love for Ivor, but [laughter]
>> No,
>> I I know what you're saying.
>> You value his his his skills on the
basketball court.
>> On the B. Of course. Of course. Right.
So, now here's what's interesting,
right?
>> Um and it it's this is in the context of
women supporting supporting their
husbands.
Um, so there's a phase in Steph's
shooting journey where I guess he was
shooting kind of from his hips, right?
>> Yeah. And that would get blocked all the
time. [laughter]
>> Well Well, even if it was working at
that early stage as
>> it wasn't going to work. That's what I'm
saying. Further. Yeah. As he grew,
right?
>> He he needed a fast release.
>> Right.
>> Well, apparently when he was making that
transition, it was really emotionally
painful. I mean like tearjerkering,
emotionally painful.
>> I I think we watched the same
documentary. I heard that. Yeah. His dad
was helping him.
>> His dad was helping him. Right.
>> Now imagine imagine if mom had demonized
the dad's effort during this period.
>> Yeah.
>> As opposed to mom explaining to him your
dad's trying to help you. And what this
point drove home to me is like
women can literally interpret
the father's contribution to the
children,
>> right?
>> Like there's a there's a there's a
rigidity that we can have as men
sometimes
in sincere love, but just the way we
approach things is, hey man, I'm really
focused on this outcome. But it's it
takes it takes a mature person that
loves them to to be like, "Okay, look,
let me in your father is trying to help
you. I need you to trust them. I assure
you." Now, obviously, I know ladies that
I'm not talking about partnering with
pathology, but I'm I'm I am talking
about helping interpret physiology,
helping interpret when it's something
good, but immature eyes wouldn't be able
to see it,
>> right? And it's significant in the
context of the importance of the
partnership.
>> Like what does I'll say Michael Jordan,
Mike Tyson, Steph Curry, um Kobe Bryant,
uh the the Williams sisters,
>> uh what do they all have in common? And
they they have in common being the the
best in their disciplines and in some
way or another being the best ever. I
love the line in I love the line in um
King Richard um in the dramatization of
the journey of the
>> um of the William sisters
>> where the father goes to Serena and he
says, "Your sister's going to go to
number one."
>> And she goes, "I know that, daddy." And
he says, "But you're going to be the
best ever.
>> [laughter]
>> Wow.
>> I mean, it's just such a powerful scene.
He's like, gonna go to number one.
>> Yeah.
>> But you're going to be the best ever. I
just mean, so there's this but but in
fairness, but fathers can be maniacal.
It can be like a maniacal focus, but it
can seem crazy
>> until you get on the other side of the
outcome.
>> And that's not to say we can't take it
too far, gentlemen. Sometimes we can
take it too far. So
>> we do need the support but I want you to
see the gentle balance that has to
happen you know
>> um but how our efforts can be
interpreted or misinterpreted
>> like so so there's that critical role
and obviously when you're able to do
that it then builds trust now I don't
know your situation so I can't speak to
it specifically I can't there are
situations where obviously you may need
to set boundaries and you might have to
distance yourself because you just are
so clear it's pathologic. I get it.
>> Okay. Um but I think over and over
sister and I are showing why you need
customized attention to your specific
social dynamics so that you can get
fantastic outcomes.
>> Yes. Yes. Perfectly said, Dr. White.
Great um great information and guys we
are at that time where an hour goes by
quick but you guys had great questions
today and Dr. Florence thank you for for
visiting us today because you definitely
um had great uh questions and u
perspective as well. And Dr. White and I
are going to um we're going to get we're
going to meet Dr. White. I'm promising
you that this week we're going to get
together and we're going to discuss
because I still think this is there's so
much still more here for men. Um but
we're going to discuss which direction
we're going to go in men's mental health
because um there's just so much and we
want to to do the best and offer you all
that we can to um just assist with this
topic. With that said, please like and
subscribe on the YouTube channel that
you are viewing on and share share with
um the man in your life um if if you
feel like this is something that would
benefit them and it is I believe that it
would um but definitely and we've this
is our number three. So there's two um
programs before um there's part one,
part two and this is part three. So you
can go back on the YouTube channel that
you are viewing from. If it's Living
Mana Church YouTube or Power of the
Lamb, you'll be able to find those and
then you can share uh with the men in
your life. But we want you guys to
continue um to this series, continue to
watch and be a part of this series with
us.
uh we'll tell you you you're going to
get some type of um advertising so you
know where we're going next week with
men's mental health. Invite somebody,
invite a friend, tell them all about it.
Um we would love to have you and them
here next week at the same time. So with
that, want to thank you guys for viewing
and we will see you next week.
Byebye everyone. Yeah.